<?xml version="1.0" encoding="windows-1252"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC0822 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC0822 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5322.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2045 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2045.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2392 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2392.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3261 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3261.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5368 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5368.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5621 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5621.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6442 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6442.xml">
]>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="std" docName="draft-ietf-sipcore-content-id-00" obsoletes="" updates="" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Content-ID in SIP">
      Content ID header field in Session Initiation Protocol (SIP)
    </title>
      <author initials="C.H." surname="Holmberg" fullname="Christer Holmberg">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Hirsalantie 11</street>
          <code>02420</code>
          <city>Jorvas</city>
          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>
        <email>christer.holmberg@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="I.S." surname="Sedlacek" fullname="Ivo Sedlacek">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Sokolovska 79</street>
          <code>18600</code>
          <city>Praha</city>
          <country>Czech Republic</country>
        </postal>
        <email>ivo.sedlacek@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2017"/>
    <area>Transport</area>
    <workgroup>SIPCORE Working Group</workgroup>
    <keyword>SIP</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>
        This document specifies the Content-ID header field for usage in the Session Initiation Protocol (SIP).
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction" toc="default">
      <section title="Identifying a body part" toc="default">
        <t>
          A SIP message consists of a start-line, one or more header fields, an
          empty line indicating the end of the header fields, and
          an optional message-body, as specified in <xref target="RFC3261" pageno="false" format="default"/>.
        </t><t>
          The message-body of the SIP message can be a non-multipart body or a multipart body as specified in <xref target="RFC3261" pageno="false" format="default"/>.
        </t><t>
          A multipart body contains zero, one or several body parts, encoded using <xref target="RFC2045" pageno="false" format="default"/> format.
        </t><t>
          A body part in the multipart body can contain a Content-ID header field with an ID value uniquely identifying the body part, as
          specified in <xref target="RFC2045" pageno="false" format="default"/>.
        </t><t>
          There is no defined method how to convey an ID value uniquely identifying the non-multipart body. The Content-ID header field is not a defined SIP header field and the non-multipart body is not a body part.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Referencing a body part" toc="default">
        <t>
          A SIP header field can contain a reference to a body part using a Content-ID URL, as specified
          in <xref target="RFC5621" pageno="false" format="default"/>.
        </t><t>
          The Content-ID URL is specified in <xref target="RFC2392" pageno="false" format="default"/>.
          <xref target="RFC2392" pageno="false" format="default"/> also specifies how to discover the body
          part referenced by a Content-ID URL.
        </t><t>
          Examples of a SIP header field referencing a body part using a Content-ID URL are:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
              <xref target="RFC6442" pageno="false" format="default"/> specifies how a Geolocation header
              field references a body part using a Content-ID URL, for providing location.
            </t><t>
              <xref target="RFC5368" pageno="false" format="default"/> specifies how a Refer-To header field
              references a body part using a Content-ID URL, to provide a list of targets.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Problem statement" toc="default">
        <t>
          Since the Content-ID header field is not a defined SIP header field and since non-multipart body is not a body part:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
            When solely one content needs to be transported in a SIP message, if a UAC does not need
            to include in the SIP message a SIP header field referencing a body part containing the content, then the UAC can set
            the message-body to a non-multiparty body containing the content.
            </t><t>
            However, when solely one content needs to be transported in a SIP message, if a UAC needs
            to include in the SIP message a SIP header field referencing a body part containing the content, then the UAC needs to set
            the message-body to a multiparty body with one body part such that the body part contains the content and associated Content-ID header field.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Examples of the problem" toc="default">
        <section title="Example 1" toc="default">
          <t>
            If a UAC sends an INVITE request conveying location as specified in
            <xref target="RFC6442" pageno="false" format="default"/>,
            if the UAC decides not to include an SDP offer, and if the location
            is conveyed by value, then the UAC needs to include only one content
            in the INVITE request.
          </t><t>
            This content contains the location information and can be e.g. of the application/pidf+xml MIME type.
          </t><t>
            However, due to <xref target="RFC6442" pageno="false" format="default"/> requiring inclusion of a Geolocation
            header field referencing the body part with the content containing the location information,
            the UAC needs to set the message-body of the INVITE request to a multipart body,
            and the UAC needs to include a body part with
            a content of the application/pidf+xml MIME type and with an associated Content-ID header field in the multipart body.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Example 2" toc="default">
          <t>
            If a UAC sends an REFER request including a list of targets as specified in <xref target="RFC5368" pageno="false" format="default"/>,
            then the UAC needs to include only one content in the REFER request.
          </t><t>
            This content contains the list of targets and is of the application/resource-lists+xml MIME type.
          </t><t>
            However, due to <xref target="RFC5368" pageno="false" format="default"/> requiring inclusion of a Refer-To header field
            referencing the body part containing the list of targets,
            the UAC needs to set the message-body of the REFER request to a multipart body,
            and the UAC needs to include a body part with
            a content of the application/resource-lists+xml MIME type and with an associated Content-ID header field in the multipart body.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section title="Solution" toc="default">
        <t>
          The Content-ID header field included in the header fields of a SIP
          message identifies a body part consisting of the message-body of a
          SIP message and metadata provided by some additional SIP header fields.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Conventions">
    <t>
      The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"></xref>.
    </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Content-ID" title="Content-ID header field">
      <section anchor="Content-ID-Introduction" title="Introduction">
        <t>
          This section defines the usage of the Content-ID header field for SIP.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Content-ID-Syntax" title="Syntax">
        <t>
          The ABNF for the Content-ID header fields is:
        </t>
        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[

   Content-ID = "Content-ID" HCOLON msg-id

   msg-id     = "<" id-left "@" id-right ">"

   NOTE: id-left and id-right are specified in [RFC5322].

   NOTE: When used in a SIP header field, the msg-id syntax has been
   simplified compared to the syntax in [RFC5322].

       ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Content-ID-Semantic" title="Semantics">
        <t>
          The Content-ID header field included in the header fields of a SIP message
          identifies a body part consisting of the message-body of the SIP message, and
          the metadata provided by:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
              the Content-ID header field itself;
            </t><t>
              a MIME-Version header field, if included in the header fields of
      the SIP message;
            </t><t>
              a Content-Disposition header field, if included in the header fields of
      the SIP message;
            </t><t>
              a Content-Encoding header field, if included in the header fields of
      the SIP message;
            </t><t>
              a Content-Language header field, if included in the header fields of
      the SIP message;
            </t><t>
              a Content-Length header field, if included in the header fields of
      the SIP message; and
            </t><t>
              a Content-Type header field, if included in the header fields of
      the SIP message.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          The Content-ID header field can be included in any SIP message which
          is allowed to contain a message-body.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="Content-ID-Procedures" title="Procedures">
        <section anchor="Content-ID-UA-Procedures" title="UA procedures">
          <t>
            A UA MAY include a Content-ID header field in any SIP message which is allowed to contain a message-body.
          </t><t>
            A UA MUST NOT include a Content-ID header field in any SIP message which is not allowed to contain a message-body.
          </t><t>
            The UA MUST set the value of the Content-ID header field to a globally unique value.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="Content-ID-proxy-Procedures" title="Proxy procedures">
          <t>
            A proxy MUST NOT add a Content-ID header field in a SIP message.
          </t><t>
            A proxy MUST NOT modify a Content-ID header field included in a SIP message.
          </t><t>
            A proxy MUST NOT delete a Content-ID header field from a SIP message.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="section.sec" title="Security considerations">
      <t>
        The Content-ID header field value MUST NOT reveal sensitive user information.
      </t><t>
        If the message-body associated with the Content-ID header field contains encrypted content, it MUST NOT be
        possible to derive a key that can be used to decrypt
        the message-body content from the Content-ID header field value.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="section.iana" title="IANA considerations">
      <t>
        This specification registers a new SIP header field according to the procedures
        in <xref target="RFC3261" pageno="false" format="default"/>.
      </t>
      <section anchor="section.iana.header" title="Header field">
        <t>[RFC EDITOR NOTE: Please replace XXXX with the RFC number of this document when publishing]</t>
        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
   RFC Number:  RFC XXXX

   Header Field Name:  Content-ID

   Compact Form:  none
       ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Change log">
      <t>
        [RFC EDITOR NOTE: Please remove this section when publishing]
      </t>
      <t>
        TBD
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative references">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2045"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2392"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5322"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3261"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5368"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5621"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6442"?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
