<?xml version="1.0" encoding="windows-1252"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2045 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2045.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2046 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2046.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2392 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2392.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3261 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3261.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5322 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5322.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5368 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5368.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5621 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5621.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6442 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6442.xml">
]>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="std" docName="draft-ietf-sipcore-content-id-01" obsoletes="" updates="" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Content-ID-in-SIP">
      Content ID header field in Session Initiation Protocol (SIP)
    </title>
      <author initials="C.H." surname="Holmberg" fullname="Christer Holmberg">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Hirsalantie 11</street>
          <code>02420</code>
          <city>Jorvas</city>
          <country>Finland</country>
        </postal>
        <email>christer.holmberg@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="I.S." surname="Sedlacek" fullname="Ivo Sedlacek">
      <organization>Ericsson</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Sokolovska 79</street>
          <code>18600</code>
          <city>Praha</city>
          <country>Czech Republic</country>
        </postal>
        <email>ivo.sedlacek@ericsson.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2017"/>
    <area>Transport</area>
    <workgroup>SIPCORE Working Group</workgroup>
    <keyword>SIP</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>
        This document specifies the Content-ID header field for usage in the Session Initiation Protocol (SIP).
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction" toc="default">
      <section title="Setting up ID value uniquely identifying body" toc="default">
        <t>
          A SIP message consists of a start-line, one or more header fields, an
          empty line indicating the end of the header fields, and
          an optional message-body, as specified in <xref target="RFC3261" pageno="false" format="default"/>.
        </t><t>
          A message-body of the SIP message can contain one body only or can contain several body parts,
          as specified in <xref target="RFC3261" pageno="false" format="default"/> and <xref target="RFC5621" pageno="false" format="default"/>.
        </t><t>
          A body part encoded using <xref target="RFC2045" pageno="false" format="default"/>
          can contain a Content-ID header field with an ID value uniquely identifying the body part, as
          specified in <xref target="RFC2045" pageno="false" format="default"/>.
        </t><t>
          However, when the message-body of the SIP message contains one body only, there is no body part specified. Thus, there is also no defined method
          how to convey an ID value uniquely identifying the body part.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Referencing the ID value uniquely identifying body" toc="default">
        <t>
          A SIP header field can contain a reference to a body part using a Content-ID URL, as specified
          in <xref target="RFC5621" pageno="false" format="default"/>.
        </t><t>
          The Content-ID URL is specified in <xref target="RFC2392" pageno="false" format="default"/>.
          <xref target="RFC2392" pageno="false" format="default"/> also specifies how to discover the body part referenced by a Content-ID URL.
        </t><t>
          Examples of a SIP header field referencing a body part using a Content-ID URL are:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
              <xref target="RFC6442" pageno="false" format="default"/> specifies how a Geolocation header
              field references a body part using a Content-ID URL, for providing location.
            </t><t>
              <xref target="RFC5368" pageno="false" format="default"/> specifies how a Refer-To header field
              references a body part using a Content-ID URL, to provide a list of targets.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Problem statement" toc="default">
        <t>
          Since the Content-ID header field is not a defined SIP header field:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
            If solely one body needs to be transported in a SIP message and the UAC does not need
            to include in the SIP message a SIP header field referencing the body part, then the UAC sets the message-body to the body.
            </t><t>
            However, if solely one body needs to be transported in a SIP message and the UAC needs
            to include in the SIP message a SIP header field referencing the body part, then the UAC sets the message-body to be of the "multipart" MIME type and includes one body part
            and associated Content-ID header field.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Examples of the problem" toc="default">
        <section title="Example 1" toc="default">
          <t>
            If a UAC sends an INVITE request conveying location as specified in <xref target="RFC6442" pageno="false" format="default"/>,
            if the UAC decides not to include an SDP offer, and if the location is conveyed by value, then the UAC needs to include
            one body only in the INVITE request.
          </t><t>
            This body contains the location information and can be e.g. of the application/pidf+xml MIME type.
          </t><t>
            However, due to <xref target="RFC6442" pageno="false" format="default"/> requiring inclusion of a Geolocation header field
            referencing the body part containing the location information,
            the UAC needs to include a message-body of "multipart/mixed" MIME type in the INVITE request,
            and the UAC needs to include a body part of the application/pidf+xml MIME type and associated Content-ID header field in the message-body of the "multipart/mixed" MIME type.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Example 2" toc="default">
          <t>
            If a UAC sends an REFER request including a list of targets as specified in <xref target="RFC5368" pageno="false" format="default"/>,
            then the UAC needs to include one body only in the REFER request.
          </t><t>
            This body contains the list of targets and is of the application/resource-lists+xml MIME type.
          </t><t>
            However, due to <xref target="RFC5368" pageno="false" format="default"/> requiring inclusion of a Refer-To header field
            referencing the body part containing the list of targets,
            the UAC needs to include a message-body of the "multipart/mixed" MIME type in the REFER request
            and the UAC needs to include a body part of the application/resource-lists+xml MIME type and associated Content-ID header field in the message-body of the "multipart/mixed" MIME type.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section title="Solution" toc="default">
        <t>
          To avoid the unnecessary usage of a message-body of a "multipart" MIME type when only
          one body needs to be included in a SIP message, this document specifies a Content-ID header field as a SIP header field.
        </t><t>
          The Content-ID header field included in header fields of a SIP message identifies a body part consisting of the message-body of the SIP message and:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
              a MIME-Version header field, if included in the header fields of the SIP message;
            </t><t>
              a Content-Disposition header field, if included in the header fields of the SIP message;
            </t><t>
              a Content-Encoding header field, if included in the header fields of the SIP message;
            </t><t>
              a Content-ID header field, if included in the header fields of the SIP message;
            </t><t>
              a Content-Language header field, if included in the header fields of the SIP message;
            </t><t>
              a Content-Length header field, if included in the header fields of the SIP message;
            </t><t>
              a Content-Type header field, if included in the header fields of the SIP message.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Conventions">
    <t>
      The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"></xref>.
    </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Content-ID" title="Content-ID header field">
      <section anchor="Content-ID-Introduction" title="Introduction">
        <t>
          This section defines the usage of the Content-ID header field for SIP.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Content-ID-Syntax" title="Syntax">
        <t>
          The ABNF for the Content-ID header fields is:
        </t><t>
          Content-ID = "Content-ID" HCOLON msg-id
        </t><t>
          NOTE: msg-id is specified in <xref target="RFC5322" pageno="false" format="default"/>.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="Content-ID-Semantic" title="Semantic">
        <t>
          A Content-ID header field included in header fields of a SIP message indicates a globally
          unique identification of a body part consisting of the message-body of the SIP message and:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>
              a MIME-Version header field, if included in the header fields of the SIP message;
            </t><t>
              a Content-Disposition header field, if included in the header fields of the SIP message;
            </t><t>
              a Content-Encoding header field, if included in the header fields of the SIP message;
            </t><t>
              a Content-ID header field, if included in the header fields of the SIP message;
            </t><t>
              a Content-Language header field, if included in the header fields of the SIP message;
            </t><t>
              a Content-Length header field, if included in the header fields of the SIP message;
            </t><t>
              a Content-Type header field, if included in the header fields of the SIP message.
            </t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>
          The Content-ID header field can be included in any SIP message which is allowed to contain
          a message-body.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="Content-ID-Procedures" title="Procedures">
        <section anchor="Content-ID-UA-Procedures" title="UA procedures">
          <t>
            A UA MAY include a Content-ID header field in any SIP message which is allowed to contain a message-body.
          </t><t>
            A UA MUST NOT include a Content-ID header field in any SIP message which is not allowed to contain a message-body.
          </t><t>
            The UA MUST set the value of the Content-ID header field to a globally unique value.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="Content-ID-proxy-Procedures" title="Proxy procedures">
          <t>
            A proxy MUST NOT add a Content-ID header field in a SIP message.
          </t><t>
            A proxy MUST NOT modify a Content-ID header field included in a SIP message.
          </t><t>
            A proxy MUST NOT delete a Content-ID header field from a SIP message.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="section.sec" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
        The Content-ID header field value MUST NOT reveal sensitive user information.
      </t><t>
        If the message-body associated with the Content-ID header field contains encrypted content, it MUST NOT be
        possible to derive a key that can be used to decrypt
        the message-body content from the Content-ID header field value.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="section.iana" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>
        This specification registers a new SIP header field according to the procedures
        in <xref target="RFC3261" pageno="false" format="default"/>.
      </t>
      <section anchor="section.iana.header" title="Header Field">
        <t>[RFC EDITOR NOTE: Please replace XXXX with the RFC number of this document when publishing]</t>
        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
   RFC Number:  RFC XXXX

   Header Field Name:  Content-ID

   Compact Form:  none
       ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Change Log">
      <t>
        [RFC EDITOR NOTE: Please remove this section when publishing]
      </t>

      <t>
        Changes in draft-ietf-sipcore-content-id-01:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>
            Clean up of section 1, including shortening introduction and cleaning up of "body" and "body part" usages.
          </t>
          <t>
            Clarify that the SIP header fields forming the body part are not required to be present in the SIP message.
          </t>
          <t>
            MIME-Version header field included as one of the SIP header fields forming the body part;
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2045"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2046"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2392"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5322"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3261"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5368"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5621"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6442"?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
